Uh we welcome back Rich Richmond Alake
who gave a workshop yesterday that got
amazing feedback. So high expectations
now Richmond. Um but this is a really
interesting one because there's a lot of
talk about context engineering. Uh but
memory engineering is is just as
important but actually far less talked
about. So really looking forward to this
session. Richmond is is the is uh the
director of AI developer experience at
Oracle and we're very very happy to have
him here with us. So please welcome on
stage Richmond.
>> Yeah, I'm Richmond Al. Nice to meet you
guys. Thank you guys for coming here
today to hear my talk um I call it
propaganda but hear my talk on memory
engineering. So we're picked off. So
there are two people there two types of
people in this room right now. Um,
there are those that get it and those
that don't. I'm going to talk about what
it is in a second. And the split is also
within the Genai industry as well within
this Genai application development.
So there was this report. How many of
you have seen this report the Genai
divide from MIT? Nice. A couple people.
And the TDR is 95% of organizations are
not realizing value from their Genai
initiatives and only 5% are. And that is
this divide within the industry. So
there's a divide in this room and
there's a divide in the industry and the
dividing line from the Genai report was
memory
intelligence and capability. So the 95%
that didn't realize value from their AI
initiatives and the 5% that did the main
difference between them was this Genai
applications that they had had some form
of adaptability,
learning capabilities and memory. So
they were building agents with memory.
So the folks that actually get it in
this room were at a workshop yesterday.
I see some of your faces here. Um, so
they get it. But by the end of this
talk, we're all going to be on the same
level. We're all going to understand
memory engineering and maybe understand
how you can actually go away and explore
this topic in your own time. My goal is
to get more people understanding
how they can actually start to close
that dividing line, how they can move
people across the Genai divide. and
that's through memory adaptability and
learning capability. So today I'm going
to be talking about memory engineering
and I'm going to be describing it in a
way that we can understand maybe through
the lens of context engineering. So how
many of you have heard of context
engineering? Hands up. Thank pretty much
everyone. So think of memory engineering
as context engineering plus.
All right. So quick intro to myself. Um
I'm a learner in the AI space. I've been
learning different stuff and when I
learn I teach as well and I've been
teaching on platforms like O'Reilly uh
for several years. I used to write for
Nvidia as well. Some of the articles are
still up there today and there's a
couple of talks I do like this on
YouTube and I've also taught a few
courses with a few folks deep learning
AI imperial college business school in
the UK and other uh platforms as well.
The key thing is and my the next kind of
shift in what I'm educating people on is
AI memory management for a Gent system.
In my personal opinion, this is the last
job to be done for engineers within AI.
And after we solve this, we're good.
It's AGI.
So, let's go. The talk is memory
engineering going beyond context
engineering. And we're just going to
kick off with understanding
this evolution. Right? We went from
prompt engineering to context
engineering and I'm about to take you to
memory engineering. There's going to be
a bunch of keywords
that I'm going to be sharing across my
talk. The key thing is I want you to
take away some key ideas. One, I want
you to understand the job to be done.
And the way from that I can explain the
job to be done for you guys building
agents. I have to take you back in time
to explain prompt engineering to and
also explain where we are now with
context engineering. Then we can
understand where we're going to go to
with memory engineering. So there are
three main ideas I'm going to give you.
The first one is prompt engineering is
maximization. Put your hands up if you
understand what I mean when I say prompt
engineer is max. Yeah, people that were
there yesterday understand. But the
point is
the techniques in prompt engineering
what we did was trying to stuff in as
much tokens or words into the context
window to make sure that this LLMs that
we use actually
give us the correct output. So there are
couple of techniques. Um we'll start off
with an example of a prompt. So this is
a prompt. Can you recommend some good
holiday destinations for me for the
summer?
So this is an example of a prompt. The
prompt engineering techniques we're
using such as few shots examples. Hands
up. Who knows few shots examples? The
prompt. Okay. Nice. Good. And what it
means is you're giving the LLM um
awareness of some some examples of the
way you want it to respond. And the more
examples you give it, the more it would
respond in the format that you desire.
Now that's fot prompting, right? Um,
again maximizing you're trying to put as
much information into this context
window. Then there was chain of thought
reasoning. Hands up if you've heard of
chain of thought. Yeah, same amount of
numbers. Um, so chain of for you're
essentially allowing the model to think
step by step through its process, right?
So again, maximization
of token stuffing the context window.
And then there is the React prompting.
There's a lot of react agents which
means it's just prompting that
essentially elicit reasoning but takes
it a bit further and allows the LLM to
look at the to have a thought to buy a
query take an action then observe the
output then decide on the next action to
take right the action will be governed
by some form of tool then the then the
observation will be the the observation
will be looking back into the tool
results then you could go through the
process again of thinking about the
obser of the observation, reasoning
about it, taking an action, then until
you get your LLM giving you a final
answer. Again, maximizing the amount of
prompts we put into the context window.
So, what is prompt engineering? Prompt
engineering is word smithing, right? Um,
it's finding the linguistic patterns
that actually allow you to make the LLM
useful and predictable in some sense.
But the limitation with prompt
engineering that we found out very
quickly was it didn't describe the job
to be done. So prompt engineering didn't
really capture the work that a lot of AI
developers were doing. And what what was
that work? I'm going there were a couple
of people in the space that agreed
especially when context engineering came
out. They agreed that prompt engineering
was too broad of a term, probably a term
that was captured and sensationalized by
the media and it became too over it
didn't really it didn't really capture
the complexity of what we had to do as
AI engineers. So people thought it was
merely crafting clever sentences, but
what it really was was
this systematic thinking of things we
put into the context window,
giving information to the context window
through techniques like retrieval
augmented generation. It was extensive
um constructions of retrieval pipelines.
So it was there was an hidden form of
engineering behind prompt engineering.
Anyway, everything end up with this
piece saying hey prompt engineering is
dead. There are other limitations such
as fragility of actually prompt tech
prompting techniques. So if you were to
change a word in your prompt it would
change the output and we couldn't use
that in production. There is also a
context ceiling. There's a there's a
context uh window length within all the
LMS we use today.
But the key takeaway is prompt
engineering is maximization. So does do
you guys agree that prompt or prompt
engineering was maximization or is
maximization? Put your hands up if you
agree. Okay, good number. Let's go. Next
one. Second idea I want to give to you
today. Context engineering is
optimization. So we maximization didn't
get the job done. So we move to this
space of optimizing the context the
information we're putting into the
context window of the LLM. So context
very simply is information about the
scenario that we're trying to operate
in. So if you have a prompt you would so
remember this prompt. Yeah. If you have
a prompt, you would add more information
that gives the LLM an understanding of
the scenario that the prompt might be
referencing to. So, for example, for the
holiday destination, I could give the
LLM uh context around the user, the user
likes and dislikes, previous holiday um
destination that the user's gone to,
previous interaction the user's had with
this um assistant, this travel
assistant. So that is context. Um,
Anthropic's piece on context engineering
actually talk about the difference
between prompt engineering and context
engineering and it's a good piece. How
many of you have read this or seen it? A
few folks which is good. It means that
there is still some good folks that can
actually go look at that piece. The key
takeaway um there a couple key
takeaways. One of the key takeaway was
they they kind of described and
summarized the shift which is we moved
away from finding words to describe the
prompt or finding words for our prompt
and we've moved into finding the right
configuration of context to pass into
LLM. So context engineering is
configuration, right? This is more
systematic. This is more programmatic
and I've looked through a bunch of blogs
and articles and papers from teams like
lang chain anthropic manners um open AI
and there's some common themes around
the techniques we're using. I think
we're all converging into the into
common patterns. So this is this context
engineering flywheel. Um it touches on
six particular themes that I'm seeing
run which is context window utilization
but another one which is context
organization and context organization
actually makes a lot of sense to me
because the human brain itself is
organized right AI is the replication of
human intelligence the human brain and
some form is organized in itself so the
context the information that we're
giving to these LLMs should have some
form of structure
should have some form of organization.
Then there is context retrieval. How we
retrieve context from data stores and
databases and file systems is important
and what retrieval we use when and where
is also important. So there's a bunch of
techniques, engineering techniques that
have been introduced by these teams.
Some teams are not using all of this.
Some are using one or more of this. I'm
going to be putting out a piece very
soon that touches on all of this context
engineering techniques. But a key
takeaway from the anthropic piece which
again you guys should read is
context engineering is a bunch of
strategies for configuring the context
window uh the context that goes into the
context window of the LLM but also
finding the optimal tokens that can
actually allow us to get the desired
behavior from our LLMs. So context
engineering was is optimization. there's
a bunch of limitation because in my
personal opinion context engineering
doesn't capture the job to be done
because when I was talking to a bunch of
engineers right and I was talking about
improving their agents and their rag
pipelines we were talking about
retrieval um ret reducing latency by uh
putting techniques like pre-filtering or
post filtering we're talking about
quantization we're talking about hybrid
retrieval um strategies right when you
use vector search with your keyword
search. So it wasn't merely context
engineering. Now there are other
limitations with the using context
engineering to describe the job to be
done. I'm going to be putting out an
extensive piece that talks more about
this. But the key takeaway is with
prompt engineering what we're doing is
what we're doing was frontloading
cognition. Right? With context
engineering, we're just trying to work
only with this short-term form of
memory, the working memory of the of the
LLM. But with memory, which is what
we're going to talk about with memory,
we go a bit further. So the key
takeaway, the second one was context
engineering is optimization. The first
one was prompt engineering is
maximization.
Memory engineering is continuation.
Right? So,
humans, I'm going to reference us a lot.
Us humans, um, humans have this
incredible
organ or wherever it is in our head, the
brain. It's been developed by nature and
it's one of the best form of
intelligence we have on this planet. And
of course, I'm biased, but the human
brain itself has different forms of
memory. Right? I can tell you my phone
number now and you will remember it
maybe for the first 5 seconds and by the
end of this talk you're going to forget
it. That's a short-term memory. And if I
ask you to think about the last birthday
you had, you could remember it. That's a
long-term memory. And it's more
specifically episodic memory. If I tell
you to think about the color red, maybe
you're thinking about blood or roses.
You're thinking that's that's
associative memory as well. So there are
different types of memory in human and
we still don't understand how memory
works in our brain um is an area of
research. Neuroscience is a thing. But
we can still take inspiration from
nature just as we did with other forms
of technology, right? So you look at
planes today, they don't flap their
wings, but the early attempts at flight
had devices where we were flapping
wings, but the plane that I took hair
wasn't flapping its wings. Um,
thank thank God for that. But yeah, so
moving on, I want to talk about agent
memory, right? Because memory
engineering is the discipline. This is
the engineering discipline. But what are
we actually engineering? Well, what are
we acting upon? We're acting upon agent
memory and agent. How many of you have
heard of the word agent memory before?
Before this talk. I want that number to
increase. Wow. Okay. I need to do more
propaganda and more talk. So, let's go.
Agent memory is is essentially the
components where data and information
moves through within an agentic system
or an AI agent. So we and [snorts] uh
within an agent memory you have three
main components. You have the external
memory. This can be a database right? It
could be a file system but you also have
um a second component which is a context
window of the LLM. Then you have the
parametric memory which is the model
weights and parameters within the LLM
itself. That never changes. That's
static. No matter what you do in your
agent that is not going to change yet
except if you go down the route of
fine-tuning. So there are three
components of agent memory. So agent
memory the way I describe it is a
computational exocortex for AI agents
and they're different forms of agent
memory. I'm not going to go through all
of this and I should remove this because
that's going to be annoying. But we're
not going to relaunch Chrome. Um
let's see. Can we escape this? No. Going
to have to go back into slido. Okay. So
there are different types of memory. So
there is short-term memory which I just
described. It's temporary. It's not
going to persist through sessions. It's
limited. You people call it scratchpad.
An example of what a short-term memory
is the working memory that we have which
can be the LLM context window or some
session memory. Semantic cache is also a
form of short-term memory. As have has
anyone heard of the word semantic cache
before?
Okay, those that haven't follow me on
LinkedIn. We're going to talk about
semantic hash very soon. Um, I don't
have enough time to explain. Those at
the workshop yesterday, they they got
the they they understand what semantic
caches and there I'm going to give you
some material as well. Long-term memory
is obvious. It's is memory that last and
persist across different session for
longer rising task. So agents need this
as well. Coordination is a special one.
When you have a multi- aent system, you
need some form of memory space for them
to act with each other and communicate
with each other. So this is something we
discovered we needed for multi- aent
system. So what is memory engineering?
Let's define it. Memory engineering is
the scaffolding that we have to build to
move data and information across the
three components of agent memory that I
just pointed out to you. That's what
memory engineering is. that that is the
job to be done. It's the job that we do
today for those that are in the front
lines that actually looking at um agent
memory and making agents actually work
in production. It's the main job they're
doing. So to define more of the job that
we're doing and you're going to get the
slide, you're going to get the slides to
define more of the jobs that we're
doing. You can think of this memory
engineering life cycle. A lot of a lot
of the folks that are building these
systems, we're ingesting data. We're
taking data and converting it into
embeddings using an embedded model.
We're storing the embeddings and the
data into a database.
Then we're also organizing that data.
Data modeling is very important when
you're working within um with AI agents
that you want to make more reliable and
capable in production. Then there's the
retrieval aspect. Vector search is not
all you need. You need to think about
hybrid search. You need to think about
quantization and ways you can optimize
your retrieval pipelines. Then you think
about the LLM processing and inference.
And what this is the part where you
actually need to actually educate more
people on is the information you get out
from your LLM. You can feed it back in.
You can store that into your database
with some form of structure and it can
be reused as well. So you have this
cycle of information passing through
your system. Okay, prompt words context.
We're trying to explain the world behind
the words. But memory and that is
blocking memory. But memory is a better
way to describe what we need from AI
today, which is personalization,
which is I want my AI agents to remember
my preference. I want them to remember
the interaction. So memory feels like a
very better word to describe where we're
going towards. So prompt engineering is
words about the world, right? It's
phrases that we want to use to describe
the world. Context engineering is world
building. It's the word we're using to
tell the LLM about the world we're in.
But memory engineering is persistence.
It's making sure that world that we're
describing continues and develops.
So we understand memory engineering
and so do a lot of people in the front
line of the space. So this came out from
Google um last week or maybe yeah last
week. Uh the team at Google were talking
about context engineering. They should
have called it memory engineering
because they just talk about sessions
and memory right they don't talk about
some of the context engineering
flywheels that we included. And this
came out from cursor a few weeks ago
talking about um how they improved their
system using semantic search and
actually retraining the embedded model
fine-tuning the embedded model using
agent traces. Then this come came out
from enthropic. The key thing is a lot
of people in the front line are
realizing the job to be done but we just
need to describe it because description
of what we do what we do as uh engineers
is very important.
So the key takeaway the third one memory
engineering is continuation. The first
one was prompt engineering is
maximization. Second context engineering
is optimization and memory engineering
is continuation. Do you guys get it?
That's good. Okay. So there's a lot of
words but there's code to this. I showed
some folks yesterday, but you can type
in, not type in, but you can go on
GitHome and type in memories and you
will see this library that I use as my
playground to explore some of this area
and bring to you uh abstractions to
allow you to play with uh to understand
memory in a sense. I'm also doing Oh,
some people are taking pictures.
Okay, we're going to I have a clicker
that I'm not using.
I'm using it now. So,
I'm also doing this thing on LinkedIn
called 100 days of agent memory. Um, I'm
on day 60. Today's day 60. So, you can
go back and look at things I spoken
about or you can just keep following,
you can follow me on this journey as I
explore this space cuz it is a journey.
So, day 60 hopefully we make it by day
100 to day 100. But the key thing is
today some of you have the the seed to
close this gap or at least move people
from one of one area of this geni divide
to the other. So you want to move people
from the 95% and get them to the 5%. And
as a bonus I'm I'm thinking about two
things and this is the bonus uh the
bonus part to the slide. I've got a few
more minutes left. There are two ideas
I'm thinking about. One is application
mode and one is the agent stack. So I'm
going to go through them very quickly.
With application mode, I'm seeing that
there's a pattern AC across all of the
agents that we're developing and they
fall within three three particular
patterns. So an agent might have one or
more of this. Um it could be a spectrum.
You're either building an assistant, a
workflow agent, or a deep research
agent. I've described it there, but I
just wanted to share that with you. So
it really helps when you're thinking
about memory to think about what am I
building and what memory type would um
associate with the application mode I'm
building. For example, a workflow agent
does not need conversational memory. All
you need is execution of sequential
steps or parallel steps. Uh a deep
research agent might need more of all of
or even all of the memory that that
we've spoken about.
So the second thing is the agent stack.
I'm going to go through this very
quickly. I'm just going to click
through. Here we go. There's the
application stack. And this is
essentially the key layers that I see
are very important for us to get right
when we're building aic systems. So this
is the blueprint of making sure we're
building reliable production ready
agentic system. The important bit is the
memory core.
If you're an AI leader, you you're going
to get the slides. So take it back. Take
some pictures. Go on. You taking it?
Okay, cool. uh if you're an AI leader,
you can look at two parts of this. The
the top part and the bottom the bottom
two parts. So the application and
interaction and the interaction layer
because you want to think about you want
to actually think about um what your
customers are experiencing. That's the
application layer. But if you're a
leader within a large organization or
small organization, you also has to be
thinking about your infrastructure and
your memory core because that's the
foundation of your entire business. So
if you if you want to take a strategic
view on it, I'm not saying you don't
think about the rest, but those are the
key areas you focus. If you're an AI
leader, try to think about where do you
want to invest. Well, you invest in your
application where your customer see, you
invest in the infrastructure as well,
the foundation, but you have to pay
particular attention to your tooling.
I'll be done in a second. And customer
experience, these are the areas I think
you should be focusing on. Of course, we
can debate this as well. And
I would miss it if I didn't mention the
fact that I'm at Oracle and I've been in
Oracle for about two and a half weeks,
which is a long time in AI. Um, but when
I got to Oracle, I was so excited
because when I opened the package, there
was so many toys to play with that
aligned with all aspects of the agent
stack. Right? So I work in Oracle
database which is the memory core but
there are other areas of Oracle's
products and features that really give
developers tools and features to
actually start to build um efficient
security uh security graded or efficient
and actually secure AI agents agents
that are reliable believable and capable
and this is the last slide of my talk so
you're going to be hearing more from me
feel free to follow me on LinkedIn or
you can come talk to me after this.
Thank you very much for listening.
[music]